<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Technology | Squid's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-01-01T07:36:47-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carin Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Embrace and Reach]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/11/02/embrace-and-reach/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-02T14:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/11/02/embrace-and-reach</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://farm1.staticflickr.com/99/290760357_01392a3f51_n.jpg">http://farm1.staticflickr.com/99/290760357_01392a3f51_n.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>One of the wonderful things about being a technologist today, is
to be part of an industry that is bubbling over with new and
exciting things. It can be exhilarating and overwhelming. How can we
try and do all these great new things?  Of course, it is not
sensible to simply drop whatever you are using and continually chase
after the newest tech.  Nor is steadfastly staying in one place and
refusing to accept that there is a better way of doing things.  The
challenge is to absorb, identify, and synthesize both good of the
what we are currently doing and the new stuff too.  We want to embrace and continue the good things that
are working for us and reach for the new technologies that will propel
us farther in the future.</p>

<p>Since everyone has their own experience synthesizing the world around
them, there are many differing opinions on what we should continue to
embrace and what we technologies and practices should reach for.  I
humbly offer my thoughts on this based from my own perspective.</p>

<h2>Embrace: Agile Feedback</h2>

<h2>Reach for: Lean Startup Discipline and Programmer Anarchy</h2>

<p>Agile has become a victim of its own success.  Becoming so big, its
message has been confused and abused in too many ways to name.  But
the core pillar of frequent and continuous feedback is a foundation to
any successful software project and should be embraced.  However, we
should not stop there.  We should reach for the rewards that <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/principles">Lean Startup
Methodology</a> offers in the form
of displinced validation.  We should also
reach to unleash the innovation of our smart developers with
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uk-CF7klLdA">Programmer Anarchy</a>, and
look for ways to ruthlessly stomp out unnecessary and wasteful
project management practices.</p>

<h2>Embrace: Ruby&rsquo;s Community</h2>

<h2>Reach for: Clojure, Go, Elixir, and Meteor</h2>

<p>Ruby and Rails have been an incredible game changer for web
development.  But they too are suffering from their own success.  One
of the strengths of Ruby, which should be embraced and nutured, is the
strength of the community and the openness to newcomers.  This strength
yields a fruitful ground for a vibrant library ecosystem, which has
helped Ruby flourish.  We need to reach beyond Ruby and Rails to other
languages and frameworks that focus on simplicity and concurrency.  The bright future
will belong to the likes of <a href="http://clojure.org/">Clojure</a>,
<a href="http://golang.org/">Go</a>, <a href="http://elixir-lang.org/">Elixir</a>, and <a href="http://www.meteor.com/">Meteor</a>.  We need
to reach and start using these in the products we build, while
encouraging the growth of a welcoming community and ecosystem like the
one we have in Ruby.</p>

<h2>Embrace: Collaboration</h2>

<h2>Reach for: the Distributed and Decentralized</h2>

<p>Collaboration with tools like Google Docs works.  We should continue
to embrace the power that this gives us. However we should embrace
tools for combining this collaboration in a truly distributed and
decentralized manner. Git itself is wonderful and distributed, but we
should reach for tools like Github to be more decentralized and resilient.
As privacy concerns grow in today&rsquo;s world.  We need to reach beyond
the convenience that a centralized source of information gives us and
truly understand the trade offs involved.</p>

<p>We live in an incredible, vibrant time.  Look around and what you
do everyday.  Embrace and nurture all the good parts, and never give up
reaching for something better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
