<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Datomic | Squid's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/categories/datomic/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-03T17:24:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carin Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conversations with Datomic - Part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2015/08/25/converstations-with-datomic-3/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-25T10:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2015/08/25/converstations-with-datomic-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://avatars0.githubusercontent.com/u/1478702?v=3&amp;s=200">https://avatars0.githubusercontent.com/u/1478702?v=3&amp;s=200</a>"></p>

<p><em>This is a continuation of the <a href="http://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2015/08/15/conversations-with-datomic/">first</a> and
<a href="http://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2015/08/19/conversations-with-datomic-part-2/">second</a> conversations in which topics such as creating databases,
learning facts, querying, and time traveling were discussed.  Today&rsquo;s topics include architecture, caching, and scaling.</em></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Hello again <a href="http://www.datomic.com/">Datomic</a>. Ready to talk again?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Sure.  I think you wanted to ask me some questions about how I would fit in with your other systems.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Yes.  Like I was saying earlier, I think your abilities to learn facts, reason about them, and keep track of the history of all those facts is really great.
I am interested in having you work with me every day, but first I want to understand your components so that I can make sure you are a good fit for us.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> I would be happy to explain my architecture to you.  Perhaps showing you this picture is the best way to start.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5723/20819693686_f9ec3852c3_z.jpg">http://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5723/20819693686_f9ec3852c3_z.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I am made of three main parts: my <em>transactors</em>, my <em>peers</em>, and my <em>storage</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Human</strong>:  What is a <em>peer</em>?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic</strong>:  A <em>peer</em> is an application that is using the peer library.  In our last conversations,  we were talking through the Clojure api with <code>datomic.api</code>.  The application, or process, that is running this api is called a peer.  There can be many of these, all having conversations with me.</p>

<p><strong>Human</strong>: The peers then talk to your <em>transactor</em>?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic</strong> Yes. The peers talk to my transactor whenever you call <code>transact</code> with the peer library.  It is the central coordinator between all the peers and processes the requests using <em>ACID</em> transactions, and then sends the facts off to storage.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Could you remind me what <em>ACID</em> stands for again?  I always forget.  The first one is <em>Atomic</em> right?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> That is right.  I am <em>Atomic</em> in that every transaction you send to me is all or nothing.  If for some reason, one part of it fails, I will reject the entire transaction and leave my database unchanged.</p>

<p>The C is for <em>Consistency</em>.  This means that I provide every peer with a consistent view of facts over time and transactions.  I provide a global ordering of transactions across all the peers with my transactor and peers will always see all the transactions up to their current time without any gaps.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> What if a peer is behind the global time?  How do they catch up to know about the new facts that were transacted by a different peer?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> After one peer sends me a successful transaction with some new facts, I will notify all the peers about them.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Cool. That takes care of the A and C in ACID. What about the I?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> It stands for Isolated.  It makes sure that even through there are many peers having conversations with me, transactions are executed serially.  This happens naturally with my transactor.  Since there is only one transactor, transactions are always executed serially.</p>

<p><strong>Human</strong>:  In the picture, why are there are two transactors then?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic</strong>:  Oh, that is for High Availability.  When I startup my system, I can launch two running transactors, but hold one in reserve.  Just on the off chance something happens to the main one, I will swap in the failover one to keep things running smoothly.</p>

<p>The final D in <em>ACID</em> is for Durability.  Once a transaction has been committed by my transactor, it is shipped off to storage for safe keeping.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> What exactly is this storage?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Instead of storing datoms, I send <em>segments</em>, which are closely related datoms,  to storage.  I have quite a few options for storage:</p>

<ul>
<li>Dev mode &ndash; which just runs within my transactor and writes to the local file system.</li>
<li>SQL database</li>
<li>DynamoDB</li>
<li>Cassandra</li>
<li>Riak</li>
<li>Couchbase</li>
<li>Infinispan memory cluster</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Human:</strong> Which one is the best to use?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> <em>The best one to use is the one that you are already have in place at work</em>.  This way, I can integrate seamlessly with your other systems.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Oh, we didn&rsquo;t really talk about caching.  Can you explain how you do that?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Certainly.  It is even worth another picture.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5630/20852217305_90506481fe.jpg">http://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5630/20852217305_90506481fe.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Each peer has a its own <em>working set</em> of recent datoms along with a index to all the rest of the datoms in storage in memory.  When the peer has a query for a datom, it first checks to see if it has it locally in its memory cache.  If it can&rsquo;t find it there, then it will ask for a segment of that datom from storage.  Storage will return that datom along with other related datoms in that segment so that the peer can cache that in memory to make it faster for the next query.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> That seems really different from other databases, where the client constantly requests queries from a server.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Yes.  When most questions can be answered from the local memory, responses are really fast.  You don&rsquo;t need to hit storage unless you really need too.  You can even add an extra layer of caching with memcached.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> That sounds great.  I can&rsquo;t wait tell you about all of our data.  We talked a bit about your querying ability earlier, can you do the same queries that our other standard relational databases do, like joins?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Oh yes.  In fact, with me, you don&rsquo;t need to specify your joins explicitly.  I use <em>Datalog</em>, which is based on logic, so my joins are implicit.  I will figure out exactly what I need to put together to answer your query without you having to spell it out for me.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Ok.  I know that I can map some of my data that is already in other database tables to you.  What about other types of irregular data, like graphs, or sparse data.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> I am actually very proud of my data model.  It is extremely flexible.  Since I store things on such a granular datom level, you don&rsquo;t need to map your logical data model to my physical model.  I can handle <em>rectangular</em> table shaped data quite happily along with graph data, sparse data, or other <em>non-rectangular</em> data.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> That sounds great.  What do I need to know about your scaling?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> I really excel at reads.  All you have to do is elastically add another peer to me for querying.  I am not really a good fit for write scale, like big data, or log file analysis.  You will find me most happy with data that is valuable information of record and has history that is important, like transaction, medical, or inventory data.  I am also really good at being flexible for development and operations since I can use many different types of storage.  I have worked with many web and cloud apps.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Thanks for answering all my questions.  I think you might fit in quite well with our other systems.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Great!</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> One more thing, this conversation has been great, but do you have any training resources for me and my other human coworkers?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Sure thing. There are a few really good resources on the <a href="http://www.datomic.com/training.html">Datomic Training Site</a>.  I would suggest watching the videos there and pairing them with:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/stuarthalloway/presentations/blob/master/Nov2014/DayOfDatomicNov2014.pdf?raw=true">The slides for the videos</a> which have the labs to work through form the videos.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Datomic/day-of-datomic">The Day of Datomic Repo</a> which has lots of great examples to play with.</li>
<li><a href="http://docs.datomic.com/">Tne Datomic Development Resources</a>, which include the docs on the <a href="http://docs.datomic.com/clojure/index.html">Clojure API</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Also, if you want to confirm that your data is good fit for me, I suggest you describe your data to the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/datomic">Datomic Google Group</a>.  They are nice and knowledgeable group of humans.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Thanks again Datomic!  I will grab another cookie and check it out!</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> What is it with humans and cookies?&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conversations with Datomic Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2015/08/19/conversations-with-datomic-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T08:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2015/08/19/conversations-with-datomic-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://avatars0.githubusercontent.com/u/1478702?v=3&amp;s=200">https://avatars0.githubusercontent.com/u/1478702?v=3&amp;s=200</a>"></p>

<p><em>The following is a continuation of the first <a href="http://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2015/08/15/conversations-with-datomic/">conversation</a> which touched on schema creation and querying.  This conversation includes learning new facts, time, and the sometimes unfortunate reality of lawyers.</em></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Hi <a href="http://www.datomic.com/">Datomic</a>.  I am back from my tea and cookies break.  I really enjoyed talking with you, could we continue our conversation?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Certainly.  Let me see, where did we leave off?</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Let me check my <a href="https://gist.github.com/gigasquid/92a1effb14fe4f6ced59">notes</a>.  Oh yes, we had created a database and filled it with facts about some dogs and owners.  You showed me how to ask you things about the facts, like which dogs liked cheese.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Ah yes.  We were just getting to the really interesting part about how I learn new facts without forgetting the past ones.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Can you please explain a bit more about how you learn new facts?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Sure.  I learn facts when you tell me to <em>add</em> a new fact about some entity, or to <em>retract</em> a fact about it.  It will probably make more sense with an example.  Let&rsquo;s take the dog with the name &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo; that I know about.  Could you please ask me about the dog and all of the attributes?</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Alright.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/pull (d/db conn) '[*] [:dog/name "Tiny"])
</code></p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong></p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id 17592186045423
 :dog/name "Tiny"
 :dog/breed "Great Dane"
 :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"}
</code>
There is an entity (dog) with the name &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo; who is a Great Dane and his favorite-treat is Cheese.  I am not really sure why the Cheese is capitalized, but I am sure it makes sense to a human.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Oh right.  Well, now that you mention it, I am not really sure about the cheese thing either. Can I just remove that fact?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Well, you can tell me to <em>retract</em> that fact by sending me a transaction in the form of <code>[:db/retract entity-id attribute value]</code>.  In the case of the dog, since the name attribute is unique, you can just give me the selector for Tiny like this <code>[:dog/name "Tiny"]</code>.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Like this?</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/transact conn [[:db/retract [:dog/name "Tiny"] :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"]])
</code></p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Exactly.  I have retracted that fact about &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;.  Go ahead and ask me about all of Tiny&rsquo;s attributes again.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Ok.  I use <code>(d/db conn)</code> for the current database value right?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Yes. But if you are going to be asking me multiple questions about this database value, you should not repeat the <code>(d/db conn)</code> all the time.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Oh. What should I do instead?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> The connection with me is like a ref.  Just like other refs, you should deref it once to get the database value and then use the value repeatedly. This single database value will provide consistency for all your queries.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> That makes sense.</p>

<p>```clojure
(def db-tiny-no-cheese (d/db conn))</p>

<p>(d/pull db-tiny-no-cheese &lsquo;[*] [:dog/name &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;])
```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong></p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id 17592186045423, :dog/name "Tiny", :dog/breed "Great Dane"}
</code></p>

<p>Tiny is a Great Dane.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> So you don&rsquo;t know anything about the <code>:dog/favorite-treat</code> for &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> At this particular time, I do not have anything to assert about the favorite-treat of Tiny.  However, I still remember everything about all the facts that you have told me.  For each transaction that you send me, I have a notion of a point in time like <em>t0</em>, <em>t1</em>, <em>t2</em>.  I have a complete database value for each one of those points in time.  In fact, you can look at <em>all</em> of my assertions and retractions that I have learned about using the <code>d/history</code> function on the database value.  This asks me to expose my history, which is normally hidden in favor of the <em>present</em>. I will return back a special database containing all the assertions and retractions across time.  Any queries that you ask me will have a fifth <em>datom</em> field to help you distinguish the difference.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  A fifth datom field?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> A <em>datom</em> consists of the following parts: the entity, the attribute, the value, transaction, and an operation which tells you if the fact was added or retracted (e a v tx op).  Why don&rsquo;t you try using the <code>d/history</code> function to ask me about all the facts having to do with Tiny?  I suggest using the datalog query</p>

<p>```clojure
&lsquo;[:find ?e ?a ?v ?tx ?op
  :in $
  :where [?e :dog/name &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;]</p>

<pre><code>     [?e ?a ?v ?tx ?op]]
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>which will return all the entity, attribute, value, transaction, and operation facts I ever knew about Tiny.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Ok.  Here goes.</p>

<p>```clojure
(d/q &lsquo;[:find ?e ?a ?v ?tx ?op</p>

<pre><code>   :in $
   :where [?e :dog/name "Tiny"]
   [?e ?a ?v ?tx ?op]]
</code></pre>

<p>  (d/history db-tiny-no-cheese))
```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong></p>

<p>```clojure</p>

<h1>{[17592186045423 63 &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;       13194139534314 true]</h1>

<p>  [17592186045423 64 &ldquo;Great Dane&rdquo; 13194139534314 true]
  [17592186045423 65 &ldquo;Cheese&rdquo;     13194139534314 true]
  [17592186045423 65 &ldquo;Cheese&rdquo;     13194139534320 false]}
```</p>

<p>During one transaction, you told me to add three facts about an entity:</p>

<ul>
<li>The <code>:dog/name</code> attribute, (which I refer to as 63), has the value of &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;.</li>
<li>The <code>:dog/breed</code> attribute, (which I refer to as 64), has the value of &ldquo;Great Dane&rdquo;.</li>
<li>The <code>:dog/favorite-treat</code> attribute, (which I refer to as 65), has the value of &ldquo;Cheese&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>


<p>During another transaction, you told me to retract a fact regarding the attribute <code>:dog/favorite-treat</code> about the same entity.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Wow, that is really cool.  Is there a way that I can <em>travel back in time</em> to see the world as it was during that first transaction?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Yes.  I am practically a Tardis.  You can use the <code>d/as-of</code> function with a database value and the transaction number and you can time travel.  Using that <em>time traveled</em> database value, you can ask me about all the facts I knew as of that time.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> I can&rsquo;t wait to try this.  Ok, let&rsquo;s go back to the time when I first asserted the fact that Tiny liked cheese.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/pull (d/as-of db-tiny-no-cheese 13194139534314) '[*] [:dog/name "Tiny"])
</code></p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Hold on.  We are time traveling!</p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id 17592186045423
 :dog/name "Tiny"
 :dog/breed "Great Dane"
 :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"}
</code></p>

<p>Tiny is a Great Dane whose favorite treat is Cheese.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Fantastic! Let&rsquo;s go back to the future now, ummm I mean present. Time is a bit wibbly wobbly.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Just take the <code>as-of</code> function off of the database value and you will be back in the <em>present</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Hmmm&hellip; Do I have to do a <em>retract</em> every time I want to change a value?  For example, the dog named Fido has a favorite treat of a Bone right now, right?</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/pull db-tiny-no-cheese '[*] [:dog/name "Fido"])
</code></p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong></p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id 17592186045421
 :dog/name "Fido"
 :dog/breed "Mix"
 :dog/favorite-treat "Bone"}
</code></p>

<p>Yes, it is a &ldquo;Bone&rdquo;.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> So, if I want to change it to be &ldquo;Eggs&rdquo;,  do I need to retract the current value of &ldquo;Bone&rdquo; first and then add the fact of &ldquo;Eggs&rdquo;?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> You certainly could do that and I would understand you perfectly.  However, if you simply assert a new value for an existing attribute, I will automatically add the retraction for you.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Cool.</p>

<p>```clojure
(d/transact conn [{:db/id [:dog/name &ldquo;Fido&rdquo;]</p>

<pre><code>               :dog/favorite-treat "Eggs"}])
</code></pre>

<p>(d/pull (d/db conn) &lsquo;[*] [:dog/name &ldquo;Fido&rdquo;])
```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic</strong></p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id 17592186045421
 :dog/name "Fido"
 :dog/breed "Mix"
 :dog/favorite-treat "Eggs"}
</code></p>

<p>Fido now has a favorite-treat of &ldquo;Eggs&rdquo;.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> This is really neat.  You <em>never</em> forget any facts?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Nope. Well, except in really exceptional circumstances that usually involve lawyers.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Lawyers?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Sigh.  Yes, well in some unique situations, you might be under a legal obligation to really <em>forget</em> certain facts and totally remove them from the database. There is a special tool that you can use to <em>excise</em> the data.  However, I will store a fact that <em>something</em> was deleted at that time. I just won&rsquo;t be able to remember <em>what</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> That doesn&rsquo;t sound fun.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> I prefer to keep all my facts intact.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> I can definitely see that. Well, on a happier subject, I have been very impressed with you during our conversations.  Having a time traveling database that can reason about facts seems like a really useful thing.  Also, you are also really nice.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Awww shucks, thanks.  For a human, you are really nice too.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> I was thinking about the possibility of you coming and working with me every day. Would you mind chatting some more to me about your architecture?  I want to understand how your would fit with our other systems.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Certainly. I would love that.  Do you want to talk about it now, or have another cookie break first?</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Now that you mention cookies&hellip; Let&rsquo;s take a short break and we will talk again soon.</p>

<p><em>(P.S. Humans, there are some great <a href="http://www.datomic.com/training.html">Datomic Training Videos</a> if you want to learn more)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conversations with Datomic]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2015/08/15/conversations-with-datomic/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-15T10:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2015/08/15/conversations-with-datomic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://avatars0.githubusercontent.com/u/1478702?v=3&amp;s=200">https://avatars0.githubusercontent.com/u/1478702?v=3&amp;s=200</a>"></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Hi <a href="http://www.datomic.com/">Datomic</a>.   I have been hearing good things about you.  I would like to talk to you and get to know you.  Is that alright?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Sure!  I would be happy to talk with you.  What language would you like to converse in?</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  I like Clojure.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  That is one of my favorites too.  You know how to setup a Leiningen project right?</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Oh yes.  What dependency should I use?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Just use <code>[com.datomic/datomic-free "0.9.5206"]</code>.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Got it.  Do you mind if I record our conversation in a namespaced file, so that I can refer back to it later?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Not a problem.  Make sure to require <code>datomic.api</code> when you set it up.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(ns conversations.datomic
  (require [datomic.api :as d]))
</code></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  All right.  I am all setup up.  I don&rsquo;t really know where to start, so maybe you can tell me a little about yourself.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  I would be happy to.  I am a database of facts.  Would you like to create a database with me?</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Sure.  How do I do that?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> For a casual conversation like this, we can use a in memory database with a uri like this:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(def uri "datomic:mem://first-conversation")
</code>
Then we can create the database and simply connect to it.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/create-database uri)
(def conn (d/connect uri))
</code></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> So, being a database, obviously you store things.  What sort of things to you store?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  I store facts about things, which I call <em>datoms</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  That sound neat.  How do I tell you a fact to store?  For example, what if I want you to store a fact about a dog, like its name?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Ah.  Well the name of a dog is an attribute.  First, you need to tell me about the name attribute, so that I can use it to store the fact for you .  You can describe the attribute in the form of a map like this:</p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)
 :db/ident :dog/name
 :db/valueType :db.type/string
 :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/one
 :db/unique :db.unique/identity
 :db/doc "Name of the Dog"
 :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}
</code>
 This map is a set of facts, (called <em>datoms</em>),  about an entity.  In this
 case, the entity is an attribute. Attributes, in turn, can be used to describe other entities, like a dog. I will explain the different parts to you.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>db/id</code> is the internal id of the fact. With <code>(d/tempid :db.part/db)</code>, I will generate it for you, so you don&rsquo;t have to worry about it.</li>
<li><code>db/ident</code> is the human readable reference for it. While I am fine just referring to the attribute by an id, humans prefer text.  This says that you can refer to this attribute by the namespaced keyword <code>:dog/name</code>.</li>
<li><code>db/valueType</code> tells me the type of the attribute.  The dog&rsquo;s name is a string.</li>
<li><code>db/cardinality</code> lets me know if there is a one-to-one relationship with the entity or not. In our case, a dog has only one name.</li>
<li><code>db/unique</code> is if that attribute is unique for an entity.  In our example case, we are saying that a dog can be uniquely identified by its name.</li>
<li><code>db/doc</code> is some documentation for humans that explains a bit more about the attribute.</li>
<li><code>db.install/_attribute</code> tells me that this is an schema attribute that I should store with the other things like it.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Human:</strong> I think I understand. Let me try one out for myself.  So dog breed would be this?</p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)
 :db/ident :dog/breed
 :db/valueType :db.type/string
 :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/one
 :db/doc "Breed of the Dog"
 :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}
</code></p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Yes!  I think you got it.  Let&rsquo;s try one more.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Ok.  How about the dog&rsquo;s favorite treat?</p>

<p><code>clojure
{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)
 :db/ident :dog/favorite-treat
 :db/valueType :db.type/string
 :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/one
 :db/doc "Dog's Favorite Treat to Eat"
 :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}
</code></p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> You got it.  Now, that you have these attributes, you can give them to me using a transaction with the connection.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Ok.  Do you want that in a specific format?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Yes.  Please send it to me using the form:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/transact conn [....facts....])
</code></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Sounds good.  I will put the dog schema datoms we discussed in a vector and call it <code>dog-schema</code> and then send it to you.</p>

<p>```clojure
(def dog-schema  [{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)</p>

<pre><code>               :db/ident :dog/name
               :db/valueType :db.type/string
               :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/one
               :db/unique :db.unique/identity
               :db/doc "Name of the Dog"
               :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}
              {:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)
               :db/ident :dog/breed
               :db/valueType :db.type/string
               :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/one
               :db/doc "Breed of the Dog"
               :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}
              {:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)
               :db/ident :dog/favorite-treat
               :db/valueType :db.type/string
               :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/one
               :db/doc "Dog's Favorite Treat to Eat"
               :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}])
</code></pre>

<p>(d/transact conn dog-schema)
```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> The transaction was fine.  I know all about those dog attributes now.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  I would like to also add a schema for owners for the dogs now.  I think I know how to describe the name of the owner, but I don&rsquo;t know how to express how the owner has dogs.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Ah. I that case you can specify the <code>db:valueType</code> as a <code>ref</code> type.  This lets me know that it references another entity.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Do I need to tell you that is a type of dog somehow?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> No.  I am pretty smart that way.  I will figure it out
  once you try to tell me about some real entities.  In fact, entities don&rsquo;t have types. A ref attribute can reference <em>any</em> entity.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Cool.  Well, in that case, here is the owner schema.  The owner has a name and some dogs.</p>

<p>```clojure
(def owner-schema [{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)</p>

<pre><code>                :db/ident :owner/name
                :db/valueType :db.type/string
                :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/one
                :db/unique :db.unique/identity
                :db/doc "Name of the Owner"
                :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}
               {:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/db)
                :db/ident :owner/dogs
                :db/valueType :db.type/ref
                :db/cardinality :db.cardinality/many
                :db/doc "Dogs of the Owner"
                :db.install/_attribute :db.part/db}])
</code></pre>

<p>(d/transact conn owner-schema)
```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  The transaction is fine.  I now know about the attributes that dogs and owners have.  Would you like to tell me some facts about specific dogs and owners?</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Yes. Bob is an owner.  He has two dogs. Fluffy is a poodle whose favorite treat is cheese, and Fido is a mixed breed, whose favorite treat is a bone.  Lucy is also an owner who has one dog named Tiny.  Tiny is a Great Dane whose favorite treat is cheese.</p>

<p>I am a bit confused how to represent the dogs of the owners. How do I do that?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  That is easy, just nest the datoms for dogs under the <code>:owner/dogs</code> attribute. You just need to create datoms for them.  Each dog or owner will by its own map.  Use <code>:db/id</code> set to <code>(d/tempid :db.part/user)</code> so I can generate it for you.  Then use each attribute from the schema as the key and let me know the value.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Like this?</p>

<p>```clojure
(d/transact conn [{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/user)</p>

<pre><code>               :owner/name "Bob"
               :owner/dogs [{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/user)
                             :dog/name "Fluffy"
                             :dog/breed "Poodle"
                             :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"}
                            {:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/user)
                             :dog/name "Fido"
                             :dog/breed "Mix"
                             :dog/favorite-treat "Bone"}]}
              {:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/user)
               :owner/name "Lucy"
               :owner/dogs [{:db/id (d/tempid :db.part/user)
                             :dog/name "Tiny"
                             :dog/breed "Great Dane"
                             :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"}]}])
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Exactly right.  I now know the facts about Bob and Lucy and their dogs.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Umm, how do I query you about the facts that your know?  For example, how do I ask you about the dog named Tiny?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  There are a couple a ways to inquire about facts I know.  To find out about the attributes of a specific dog, or entity, I would recommend using <code>d/pull</code>.  You can ask me in the form of this to get all the attributes for a given dog name.  Note that this works since the dog name is a way to uniquely identify the dog:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/pull (d/db conn) '[*] [:dog/name "Tiny"])
</code></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  What is the <code>(d/db conn)</code> all about?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  That function returns the current database value of the connection. The facts I know change during time.  Every time there is a transaction, I consider the time to be different and there is a new database value.  The <code>d/db</code> function gives you the most recent value that I know about.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> I am assuming the <code>[*]</code> is a wildcard that means give me all the attributes for that dog?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Exactly right.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> Ok.  Tell me about Tiny.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/pull (d/db conn) '[*] [:dog/name "Tiny"])
</code></p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>
<code>clojure
{:db/id 17592186045424
 :dog/name "Tiny"
 :dog/breed "Great Dane"
 :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"}
</code></p>

<p>Tiny is a Great Dane that has a favorite treat of Cheese.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  This is fun.  What about more complicated questions.  How do I ask about the name of the owner of the dog &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  For that I would ask using the <em>datalog</em> query <code>d/q</code>.  It uses logic to unify your query with all of my facts and give you the result.  The query itself would be a vector with logic statements inside like:</p>

<p>```clojure
&lsquo;[:find ?owner-name
  :where [?dog :dog/name &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;]</p>

<pre><code>     [?owner :owner/dogs ?dog]
     [?owner :owner/name ?owner-name]]
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Whoa.  What is the deal with those question marks?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> The things with the question marks are considered as variables that we will <em>unify</em> to find the answer.  For example, we are looking for something that we are going to call <code>?owner-name</code>. I am going the use the following constraints with my facts to try to find the answer:</p>

<ul>
<li>There is an entity that we are going to call <code>?dog</code> that has the attribute <code>:dog/name</code> that is &ldquo;Tiny&rdquo;</li>
<li>There is an entity that we are going to call <code>?owner</code> that has an attribute <code>:owner/dogs</code> that is the same as the <code>?dog</code> entity</li>
<li>That same <code>?owner</code> entity also has an attribute <code>:owner/name</code> that has the value <code>?owner-name</code></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Alright, so when I ask for this query, do I need to give you a database value too?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Yes.  They should have the form of:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(d/q '[datalog-query] db-value)
</code></p>

<p>Remember, to get the current db value use <code>(d/db conn)</code>.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Ok.  Here we go.</p>

<p>```clojure
(d/q &lsquo;[:find ?owner-name</p>

<pre><code>   :where [?dog :dog/name "Tiny"]
          [?owner :owner/dogs ?dog]
          [?owner :owner/name ?owner-name]]
 (d/db conn))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong></p>

<p>The answer is:</p>

<p>```clojure</p>

<h1>{[&ldquo;Lucy&rdquo;]}</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  What if I want to pass the dog name as a parameter?  How do I communicate that to you?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  You will need to use an <code>in</code> clause in the query like this:</p>

<p><code>clojure
'[:find [blah]
   :in $ ?dog-name
   :where [blah]]
</code></p>

<p>The $ is shorthand for the database value and the <code>?dog-name</code> is what you will pass in as a parameter in the query after the db-value.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Like this?</p>

<p>```clojure
(d/q &lsquo;[:find ?owner-name</p>

<pre><code>   :in $ ?dog-name
   :where [?dog :dog/name ?dog-name]
          [?owner :owner/dogs ?dog]
          [?owner :owner/name ?owner-name]]
 (d/db conn) "Tiny")
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Exactly right.  The answer is Lucy again.</p>

<p>```clojure</p>

<h1>{[&ldquo;Lucy&rdquo;]}</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  I think I am getting the hang of this!  Another quick question.  How would I go about asking you which dogs have cheese as their favorite treat?  I would want the dog&rsquo;s name and breed back.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  You would simply construct another datalog query.  This time I would recommend that you combine the <code>pull</code> syntax within the <code>find</code> part of the query.  The <code>pull</code> syntax is great at selecting attributes from an entity.  So the <code>find</code> part would look something like this:</p>

<p><code>clojure
[(pull ?dog [:dog/name :dog/breed]) ...]
</code></p>

<p>This will return the attributes of the <code>:dog/name</code> and the <code>:dog/breed</code>.  The three dots on the end will let me know that you want a collection returned, so I will give you back a simple vector with the entity attributes requested, instead of the set of vectors I normally give back.</p>

<p>The <code>where</code> section of the query is going to look for the <code>?dog</code> entity that matches the <code>:dog/favorite-treat</code> attribute with &ldquo;Cheese&rdquo;.</p>

<p><code>clojure
'[:find [(pull ?dog [:dog/name :dog/breed]) ...]
  :where [?dog :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"]]
</code></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Then I put it together with the current database value in a <code>d/q</code> function?</p>

<p>```clojure
(d/q &lsquo;[:find [(pull ?dog [:dog/name :dog/breed]) &hellip;]</p>

<pre><code>   :where [?dog :dog/favorite-treat "Cheese"]]
 (d/db conn))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong> Yup.  The answer is:</p>

<p><code>clojure
[{:dog/name "Fluffy", :dog/breed "Poodle"}
 {:dog/name "Tiny", :dog/breed "Great Dane"}]
</code></p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong>  Thanks so much.  I think I beginning to get the hang of schemas and queries.  What other things do I need to know about you?</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  Well, you have just scratched the surface really.  One of the most interesting things about me is that I never forget facts.  You can add new facts, like Tiny&rsquo;s favorite food is now hotdogs, but I won&rsquo;t forget that he liked cheese at another point in time.</p>

<p><strong>Human:</strong> That sounds really interesting.  I think I need some tea and cookies before I delve into that.  Let&rsquo;s take a short break and talk again soon.</p>

<p><strong>Datomic:</strong>  My pleasure.  I look forward to it.</p>

<p><em>Special thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/ohpauleez">Paul deGrandis</a> for
the conversation idea :)</em></p>

<p><em>(P.S. Humans, there are some great <a href="http://www.datomic.com/training.html">Datomic Training Videos</a> if you want to learn more)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
