<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Drone | Squid's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/categories/drone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-05T20:06:19-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carin Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demoing with Drones: Tips and Warnings]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/07/15/demoing-with-drones-tips-and-warnings/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-15T15:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/07/15/demoing-with-drones-tips-and-warnings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately, I have had the pleasure of speaking and sharing my experience
of programming <a href="http://ardrone2.parrot.com/">AR Drones</a> with Clojure.  However, doing live hardware
demos has not always been a smooth ride.  In fact, it can be fraught
with peril.  I thought that I would share some of the tips and tricks
that have helped me, as well as help make you
aware of some potential pitfalls.</p>

<h2>Traveling with the AR Drone</h2>

<p><img class="left <a" src="href="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5332/9301848814_1633857d6d.jpg">http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5332/9301848814_1633857d6d.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Do you need to take your drone with you on the plane to the demo?
The box that the drone comes in is a very nice carrying case, however it
is too big to take on as a carry-on.  I found that taking the hull
off, and packing it into a plastic box worked well.  It was small
enough to pack under the seat of even the smaller planes.  I took the
battery out and packed it in my checked luggage.</p>

<h2>Before the Demo</h2>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Put colored masking tape on the floor</strong> : If the floor is
  featureless, the drone will have a hard time staying in one place
  while it is hovering.  Put down some strips of colored masking
  tape in the area that you want to demo the drone.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Charge the spare battery</strong>:  Make sure that you have at least 2
  batteries charged and ready to go.  If there is an extra plug
  nearby, just plug in the battery and charger until you are ready
  to present.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Beware the network interference</strong>:  In some larger venues, like
  hotels, the network traffic will make things break.  In
  particular, receiving navigation data back from the drone. There
  are possible strategies for mitigating this &ndash; the only one I have
  tried so far is to bump up the timeout on the UDP connection.
  Other things that you may want to try would be to auto-reconnect
  after timeout.  Also limiting the amount navdata you need might
  also work.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Backup videos</strong> &ndash; Having backup videos of your demo actually
  working is essential.  It is safety net that will allow you to
  sleep the night before.  Like they say, &ldquo;Hope for the best, but
  plan for the worst&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Rehearse</strong> &ndash; If possible, go through your drone demos in the space
  sometime before the talk.  You will get a feeling for issues that
  might occur &ndash; like network troubles.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Demo Time!</h2>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Front row drone catchers</strong> &ndash; Enlist the aid of your audience.
  Show the people in the front row how to catch a drone safely and
  hold it at a 90 degree angle so the engine cuts out.  That way, if
  the drone starts going off in unplanned ways, you will have help.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cross your fingers and have fun</strong> &ndash; Good luck.  Hardware demos are
  a lot of fun.  Hopefully, everything we work as planned, but if
  not &ndash; at least it was interesting.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
