<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: all | Squid's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/categories/all/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-03T18:23:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carin Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guide to Leaving your Mac Laptop]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/12/26/guide-to-leaving-your-mac-laptop/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/12/26/guide-to-leaving-your-mac-laptop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/11572063123_6baf3b35c2.jpg">http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/11572063123_6baf3b35c2.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I felt like I was in a controlling relationship headed downhill.
After two custom laptops returned for defective hardware, I wanted to
leave.  But leaving didn&rsquo;t seem so easy after living in the walled
garden of Apple all those years.</p>

<p>This blog post is about how to leave your Mac and return to OSS.</p>

<h2>Make a New Plan, Stan</h2>

<p>There are quite a few nice alternatives to the Mac Air out there.
I decided to go with the new
<a href="http://www.dell.com/us/business/p/xps-13-linux/pd">Sputnik 3</a>.
Some of my reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>Powerful &ndash; New Haswell processor</li>
<li>13.3 inch touch display with 1920 x 1080 resolution</li>
<li>Ships with Ubuntu 12.04 (64 bit)</li>
<li>Nice design (yes looks are important)</li>
</ul>


<p>It arrived a couple of days before Christmas. The packaging itself
was quite nice.  Here is a picture next
to my 13 inch Mac Air.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7334/11572078553_7efe0e609e.jpg">http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7334/11572078553_7efe0e609e.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>The best was that everything just &ldquo;worked&rdquo; out of the box.
I had no problems configuring Ubuntu and getting the wireless network
hooked up.  I could close the lid and reopen it and have &ldquo;instant on&rdquo;
just like the Mac Air.  The keyboard is enjoyable to use and nicely
backlit.  The sleek design and light weight of the laptop is very
comparable to the Mac Air.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3753/11571869965_06975d698c.jpg">http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3753/11571869965_06975d698c.jpg</a>"></p>

<h2>Hop on the Bus, Gus</h2>

<p>It took my about a day to set up all my programs that I use on a daily
basis.
Here is a overview:</p>

<h4>Application Dock/ Organization &ndash; Dash</h4>

<p>Ubuntu has a dock on the left hand side of the screen, that is very
similar to the mac one.  You can right click and pin applications to
the dock to keep them in there. Clicking into the dash option, you can
browse your applications that are installed.</p>

<h4>Getting New Apps &ndash; Ubuntu Software Center or apt-get</h4>

<p>You can install new applications easily by using the Ubuntu Software
Center.  Browsing the applications and installing them is point and
click easy. If you don&rsquo;t see the one you need or need a more recent
version, you can always install via the command line with</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install package-name
</code></pre>

<h4>Browser &ndash; Firefox or Chromium</h4>

<p>Ubuntu comes with Firefox and Chromium installed.
You can also go with Chrome of course.</p>

<h4>Mail &ndash; Thunderbird</h4>

<p>Ubuntu comes with Thunderbird mail ready to go.
I was pleasantly surprised by how easy it was to setup Thunderbird
Mail.  You simply put in your email and password.  Ubuntu keeps a
configuration list of commonly used email providers.  It automagically
figured out the correct domains and ports to use. On the downside, it
doesn&rsquo;t do anything magic with your contacts. So you are on your own
there.  I also just found out about
<a href="http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2013/10/geary-0-4-released-with-new-look-new-features">Geary</a>,
which looks pretty sweet.</p>

<h4>Password Management &ndash; 1 Password Anywhere + Dropbox / LastPass</h4>

<p>There is not a linux client for 1Password. I can still use it by using
<a href="http://help.agilebits.com/1Password3/1passwordanywhere.html">1PasswordAnywhere</a>.
I just have a bookmark to the 1PasswordAnyway link and I haz my
logins. I am switching over to LastPass though, so you can edit / add
new passwords. There is also an import utility to move stuff over from 1Password.</p>

<h4>Emacs</h4>

<p>Emacs just works :)
It might be just me, but I think it is happier back on Ubuntu.
I did an apt-get to get the 24 version.</p>

<h4>Git Client</h4>

<p>I went with gitg for a graphical Git client. It seems to have all the
things you need.</p>

<h4>Terminal &ndash; Byobu</h4>

<p><a href="http://byobu.co/">Byobu Terminal</a> comes already installed in Ubuntu. I have been taking
it for a test drive and really like some of the features of easily
adding new tabs, splitting screens and re-attaching to sessions.</p>

<h4>Evernote/ Everpad</h4>

<p>With
<a href="http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2012/09/use-evernote-in-ubuntu-with-everpad">Everpad</a>,
I can still use all my evernote stuff too.</p>

<h4>Presentations &ndash; LibreOffice / Reveal.js</h4>

<p>I have used Keynote heavily on the Mac.  For existing presentations, I
can convert them to ppt format and then modify or run in LibreOffice
Impress. Most likely with all my new presentations, I will just use a
JavaScript framework like <a href="http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/#/">reveal.js</a></p>

<h4>Communication &ndash; Hipchat / Skype/ Google Hangouts / Campfire</h4>

<p>We use Hipchat for messaging at work.  Hipchat has a linux client
that works just the same.  Skype also has a linux client.  Of course,
Google Hangouts is just fine on the web.  I also use Campfire
sometimes. There are a couple of linux clients out there, but I
haven&rsquo;t tried them yet.  The web version works fine for me right now.</p>

<h4>iPhone</h4>

<p>On my mac, I used to plug in my phone and sync to my dropbox.  I tried
plugging in my phone, but unfortunately, iOS7 put in a security
feature to that prevents having the phone connect properly.  The
solution for me is to just use the phone dropbox app to sync the
pictures automatically to my Dropbox.</p>

<h2>Get Yourself Free</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t expect the road to free of bumps.  I have only been using my
new laptop for a week.  But so far, it has been an enjoyable switch.
The hardware is really impressive, and it feels good getting back to
OSS.</p>

<p>Best of all, I set myself free.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
