<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: All | Squid's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/categories/all/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-05-03T09:22:53-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carin Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Staying Technical]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2018/03/04/on-staying-technical/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-04T11:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2018/03/04/on-staying-technical</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was 10 years into my career when I met her. I could count the number of other women programmers I had worked with on one hand and none of them had young children at home like me. She was not only incredibly experienced and competent, but also had a son in college. I was curious about her career path so I asked her one day at lunch why she was still programming and hadn’t become a manager instead.</p>

<p>She smiled at me kindly and replied, &ldquo;I’ve worked very hard to stay exactly where I am&rdquo;,  and I was enlightened.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Self Publishing for the Creative Coder]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2017/05/27/self-publishing-for-the-creative-coder/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-27T14:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2017/05/27/self-publishing-for-the-creative-coder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, you have an idea for a fiction book. First, let me tell you that it&rsquo;s a good idea and it&rsquo;s a great thing that you are a coder. Quite a few successful authors have a background in software development. <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2543164/">Arrival</a>, (which is a fabulous movie), comes from the book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Stories-Your-Life-Others-Chiang/dp/1101972122">Stories of your Life</a>,  written by a fellow programmer <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted_Chiang">Ted Chiang</a>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Stross">Charlie Stross</a> is another fine example. One of my favorites is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Suarez_(author">Daniel Suarez</a>, the author of the<a href="https://www.amazon.com/DAEMON-Daniel-Suarez/dp/0451228731"> Daemon</a> and more recently <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Change-Agent-Novel-Daniel-Suarez/dp/110198466X/">Change Agent</a>. So yes, you can write a fiction book and you&rsquo;re in good company. This post is dedicated to help make it happen.</p>

<h2>So how do you know about self publishing?</h2>

<p>Two years ago, I had a semi-crazy idea for a tween/teen scifi book. At the time, my daughter was into all the popular books of time like <em>Hunger Games</em> and <em>Divergent</em>. The thing that I really liked about them was the strong female protagonist. The only thing that I thought was missing was a story that focused on a girl who could code. It would make it even better if she had <em>coding super powers</em>. The idea for <a href="http://www.codeshifterbook.com/">Code Shifter</a> was born. One of the things that I wanted to explore in writing the book was to have real programming code in the book but not have it be a <em>learning how to code</em> book. The code would exist as part of the story and if the reader picked up concepts along the way, great. Even if they didn&rsquo;t, it would lay the positive groundwork to have them be more open to it later.</p>

<p>Books, like software, always take longer than you plan. My daughter and I enjoyed working on it together and over time it grew into a book that we could share with others. Along the way, I learned quite a bit about writing books, publishing, and other things that I wish I had known beforehand.</p>

<h2>What did you use to write the book?</h2>

<p>In the book world, your story is referred to as your <em>manuscript</em>. As a tool to produce it, I cannot speak highly enough of <a href="https://leanpub.com/">Leanpub</a>. I found it easy and productive to work in as a programmer. For example,  my setup was pretty painless.</p>

<p>In the repo, I had a <code>manuscript</code> directory, in which there was a <code>Book.txt</code> file that listed the chapter files.</p>

<pre><code>chapter2.txt
chapter3.txt
chapter4.txt
chapter5.txt
</code></pre>

<p>Each chapter file in turn was written in markdown. For example, <code>chapter2.txt</code> looked like this:</p>

<pre><code># 1

## Flicker


Twelve-year-old Eliza knew that the next words were the result of computer program far more intelligent than any one of them. Standing next to her parents, she held her breath and watched as her brother touched his finger to the message on the wall screen.
</code></pre>

<p>From there, my process looked like:</p>

<ul>
<li>Write a bit in my favorite editor, (Emacs of course), and make a commit.</li>
<li>Push the commit to github, which is registered with the Leanpub project</li>
<li>Log onto the Leanpub project and hit the <em>preview</em> button. This would generate a pdf and ebook that I could share with my daughter for feedback.</li>
</ul>


<p>{% img <a href="http://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4274/34768029762_3bbae300f0.jpg">http://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4274/34768029762_3bbae300f0.jpg</a> %}</p>

<h3>Advantages of Leanpub for development.</h3>

<p>As I said earlier, I&rsquo;m a fan. Using git for revisions is incredibly useful. I shudder to think of people writing in Word without version control. The ability to easily create PDF and ebook formats was also very convenient. The markdown format has excellent code support. There is also the option as publishing your work as you go. However, I think that this is more useful with a technical book than with fiction.</p>

<h3>Disadvantages of Leanpub for development</h3>

<p>If you are going to work with an freelance editor or share your work with someone in the mainstream book world, they are not going to want pdf. They usually want a doc version. It took me a bit of research to find a good converter, <a href="http://pandoc.org/">pandoc</a>. With it, you can convert from markdown to Word with things looking pretty good. Don&rsquo;t try to do pdf to Word. I found it a big recipe for fail.</p>

<p>Finally, the book was considered done enough to think about publishing.</p>

<p>There was much rejoicing.</p>

<h2>Didn&rsquo;t you want to get the book into bookstores?</h2>

<p>Of course. That would be incredibly cool. However, that requires getting into what they call <em>traditional publishing</em> and it is a lot more work, time, and luck. If you go this route, you will need to budget at least six months to send out form letters to agencies to have them represent your work. Also, beware of predatory services that take advantage of unsuspecting and wide eyed authors. If you are interested in this, you&rsquo;ll want to start looking for agents that are interested in your type of book. <a href="https://querytracker.net/">Query Tracker</a> is a great place to start.</p>

<h2>Traditional publishing sounds hard. What about self publishing?</h2>

<p>Self publishing is certainly an easier more direct way to bring your book to life. For me, it was the best way forward. Luckily, Leanpub made it pretty painless.</p>

<h3>Publishing the book with Leanpub</h3>

<p>Actually publishing the finished copy was really easy with Leanpub. All I had to do was fill in some fields on the project page and push <em>Publish!</em> The book was immediately ready to share with the world. Putting out an updated edition was as easy as pushing the button again. Leanpub provides online reading as well as all the ebook versions.</p>

<p>That was nice, but I really wanted a print copy too.</p>

<h3>Publishing with CreateSpace</h3>

<p>Amazon&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.createspace.com/">CreateSpace</a> provides and excellent platform for on-demand print copies of books. This is where Leanpub comes in handy again. There is an <code>Export Option</code> that provides and unbranded pdf copy of your manuscript with all the correct formatting and margins required for CreateSpace. I simply exported the file and then uploaded it up to the project.</p>

<p>{% img <a href="http://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4203/34121511063_b63d283086_b.jpg">http://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4203/34121511063_b63d283086_b.jpg</a> %}</p>

<p>The other thing that you will want is a nice cover. There are services through CreateSpace for cover creation that you can buy or you can upload your own file. I was lucky enough to have a talented graphic designer as sister, Kristin Allmyer,  who made me an awesome cover.</p>

<p>One of the confusing things was picking an ISBN for the print copy. You don&rsquo;t need to worry about this for ebook versions but you do for a physical copy. Your choices through CreateSpace are using a provided one for free or buying your own for $99. I chose my own so I could have flexibility of working with another publisher other than Amazon if I want. If you choose that option, you can also make up your own publisher name. Mine is <em>Gigasquid Books</em>.</p>

<p>{% img <a href="http://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4244/34121511083_15027c4571.jpg">http://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4244/34121511083_15027c4571.jpg</a> %}</p>

<p>Once you have completed all the setup, they will send you a physical copy in the mail to approve. The moment you get to hold it in your hands is really magical.</p>

<p>{% img <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/C8xBM-nXYAAOmK0.jpg:large">https://pbs.twimg.com/media/C8xBM-nXYAAOmK0.jpg:large</a> %}</p>

<p>If it looks alright, you hit the approve button and voilà - it&rsquo;s for sale on Amazon!</p>

<h3>Publishing with Direct Kindle Publishing</h3>

<p>With CreateSpace, you have the option of porting your book to a Kindle format as well. It will do most of the heavy lifting of converting the files for you and a few button clicks later you have both an Kindle and print version available for your readers.</p>

<p>If you need to update the text of the Kindle version, Leanpub also has an export option available to produce unbranded ebook files. Just take this and upload it to your KDP account and you are good to go.</p>

<h2>Did you run into any problems?</h2>

<p>Of course I did. I was totally new to self publishing and I underestimated how hard copy editing is. Some errors unfortunately made it into the first version. Luckily, I had some really nice people that helped my fix it for later versions. Many thanks to Martin Plumb, Michael Daines, Paul Henrich, and S. Le Callonnec for editing help.</p>

<p>This brings me to my next point. If I had to do it all over again, I would publish the book in a different order. Books are really no different than software. There are going to be bugs when you first release it in the wild. It is best to embrace this. In the future, I would publish the ebook versions first, which are much easier to update and then the print versions after that.</p>

<h2>Did you make lots of money from the book sales?</h2>

<p>Hahaha &hellip;  that&rsquo;s funny. If you are interested in making money, books are not the best way to go. The margins on Leanpub are definitely better than Amazon, but if I really was interested in making money, I would have been much better off using deep learning to make a stock market predictor or code up a startup that I could sell off.</p>

<p>Authors in general, are much harder pressed to make livings than software developers. We should count our blessings.</p>

<h2>Any last words of advice?</h2>

<p>There is a great joy from creating a story and sharing it with others. Take your book idea, nurture it, and bring it to life. Then publish it and we can celebrate together.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guide to Leaving Your Mac Laptop]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/12/26/guide-to-leaving-your-mac-laptop/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2013/12/26/guide-to-leaving-your-mac-laptop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img <a href="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/11572063123_6baf3b35c2.jpg">http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/11572063123_6baf3b35c2.jpg</a> %}</p>

<p>I felt like I was in a controlling relationship headed downhill.
After two custom laptops returned for defective hardware, I wanted to
leave.  But leaving didn&rsquo;t seem so easy after living in the walled
garden of Apple all those years.</p>

<p>This blog post is about how to leave your Mac and return to OSS.</p>

<h2>Make a New Plan, Stan</h2>

<p>There are quite a few nice alternatives to the Mac Air out there.
I decided to go with the new
<a href="http://www.dell.com/us/business/p/xps-13-linux/pd">Sputnik 3</a>.
Some of my reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>Powerful - New Haswell processor</li>
<li>13.3 inch touch display with 1920 x 1080 resolution</li>
<li>Ships with Ubuntu 12.04 (64 bit)</li>
<li>Nice design (yes looks are important)</li>
</ul>


<p>It arrived a couple of days before Christmas. The packaging itself
was quite nice.  Here is a picture next
to my 13 inch Mac Air.</p>

<p>{% img <a href="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7334/11572078553_7efe0e609e.jpg">http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7334/11572078553_7efe0e609e.jpg</a> %}</p>

<p>The best was that everything just &ldquo;worked&rdquo; out of the box.
I had no problems configuring Ubuntu and getting the wireless network
hooked up.  I could close the lid and reopen it and have &ldquo;instant on&rdquo;
just like the Mac Air.  The keyboard is enjoyable to use and nicely
backlit.  The sleek design and light weight of the laptop is very
comparable to the Mac Air.</p>

<p>{% img  <a href="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3753/11571869965_06975d698c.jpg">http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3753/11571869965_06975d698c.jpg</a> %}</p>

<h2>Hop on the Bus, Gus</h2>

<p>It took my about a day to set up all my programs that I use on a daily
basis.
Here is a overview:</p>

<h4>Application Dock/ Organization - Dash</h4>

<p>Ubuntu has a dock on the left hand side of the screen, that is very
similar to the mac one.  You can right click and pin applications to
the dock to keep them in there. Clicking into the dash option, you can
browse your applications that are installed.</p>

<h4>Getting New Apps - Ubuntu Software Center or apt-get</h4>

<p>You can install new applications easily by using the Ubuntu Software
Center.  Browsing the applications and installing them is point and
click easy. If you don&rsquo;t see the one you need or need a more recent
version, you can always install via the command line with</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install package-name
</code></pre>

<h4>Browser - Firefox or Chromium</h4>

<p>Ubuntu comes with Firefox and Chromium installed.
You can also go with Chrome of course.</p>

<h4>Mail - Thunderbird</h4>

<p>Ubuntu comes with Thunderbird mail ready to go.
I was pleasantly surprised by how easy it was to setup Thunderbird
Mail.  You simply put in your email and password.  Ubuntu keeps a
configuration list of commonly used email providers.  It automagically
figured out the correct domains and ports to use. On the downside, it
doesn&rsquo;t do anything magic with your contacts. So you are on your own
there.  I also just found out about
<a href="http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2013/10/geary-0-4-released-with-new-look-new-features">Geary</a>,
which looks pretty sweet.</p>

<h4>Password Management - 1 Password Anywhere + Dropbox / LastPass</h4>

<p>There is not a linux client for 1Password. I can still use it by using
<a href="http://help.agilebits.com/1Password3/1passwordanywhere.html">1PasswordAnywhere</a>.
I just have a bookmark to the 1PasswordAnyway link and I haz my
logins. I am switching over to LastPass though, so you can edit / add
new passwords. There is also an import utility to move stuff over from 1Password.</p>

<h4>Emacs</h4>

<p>Emacs just works :)
It might be just me, but I think it is happier back on Ubuntu.
I did an apt-get to get the 24 version.</p>

<h4>Git Client</h4>

<p>I went with gitg for a graphical Git client. It seems to have all the
things you need.</p>

<h4>Terminal - Byobu</h4>

<p><a href="http://byobu.co/">Byobu Terminal</a> comes already installed in Ubuntu. I have been taking
it for a test drive and really like some of the features of easily
adding new tabs, splitting screens and re-attaching to sessions.</p>

<h4>Evernote/ Everpad</h4>

<p>With
<a href="http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2012/09/use-evernote-in-ubuntu-with-everpad">Everpad</a>,
I can still use all my evernote stuff too.</p>

<h4>Presentations - LibreOffice / Reveal.js</h4>

<p>I have used Keynote heavily on the Mac.  For existing presentations, I
can convert them to ppt format and then modify or run in LibreOffice
Impress. Most likely with all my new presentations, I will just use a
JavaScript framework like <a href="http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/#/">reveal.js</a></p>

<h4>Communication - Hipchat / Skype/ Google Hangouts / Campfire</h4>

<p>We use Hipchat for messaging at work.  Hipchat has a linux client
that works just the same.  Skype also has a linux client.  Of course,
Google Hangouts is just fine on the web.  I also use Campfire
sometimes. There are a couple of linux clients out there, but I
haven&rsquo;t tried them yet.  The web version works fine for me right now.</p>

<h4>iPhone</h4>

<p>On my mac, I used to plug in my phone and sync to my dropbox.  I tried
plugging in my phone, but unfortunately, iOS7 put in a security
feature to that prevents having the phone connect properly.  The
solution for me is to just use the phone dropbox app to sync the
pictures automatically to my Dropbox.</p>

<h2>Get Yourself Free</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t expect the road to free of bumps.  I have only been using my
new laptop for a week.  But so far, it has been an enjoyable switch.
The hardware is really impressive, and it feels good getting back to
OSS.</p>

<p>Best of all, I set myself free.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
