<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Deep Learning | Squid's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/categories/deep-learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-07-02T14:15:23-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carin Meier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breakfast With Zero-Shot NLP]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2021/03/15/breakfast-with-zero-shot-nlp/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-15T09:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2021/03/15/breakfast-with-zero-shot-nlp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.imgflip.com/51ror1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>What if I told you that you could pick up a library model and instantly classify text with arbitrary categories without any training or fine tuning?</p>

<p>That is exactly what we are going to do with <a href="https://joeddav.github.io/blog/2020/05/29/ZSL.html">Hugging Face&rsquo;s zero-shot learning model</a>. We will also be using <a href="https://github.com/clj-python/libpython-clj">libpython-clj</a> to do this exploration without leaving the comfort of our trusty Clojure REPL.</p>

<h3>What&rsquo;s for breakfast?</h3>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start off by taking some text from a recipe description and trying to decide if it&rsquo;s for breakfast, lunch or dinner:</p>

<p><code>"French Toast with egg and bacon in the center with maple syrup on top. Sprinkle with powdered sugar if desired."</code></p>

<p>Next we will need to install the required python deps:</p>

<p><code>pip install numpy torch transformers lime</code></p>

<p>Now we just need to set up the libpython clojure namespace to load the Hugging Face transformers library.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(ns gigasquid.zeroshot
  (:require
   [libpython-clj2.python :as py :refer [py. py.. py.-]]
   [libpython-clj2.require :refer [require-python]]))


(require-python '[transformers :bind-ns])
</code></pre>

<p>Setup is complete. We are now ready to classify with zeroshot.</p>

<h4>Classify with Zero Shot</h4>

<p>To create the classifier with zero shot, you need only create it with a handy pipeline function.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def classifier (py. transformers "pipeline" "zero-shot-classification"))
</code></pre>

<p>After that you need just the text you want to classify and category labels you want to use.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def text "French Toast with egg and bacon in the center with maple syrup on top. Sprinkle with powdered sugar if desired.")

(def labels ["breakfast" "lunch" "dinner"])
</code></pre>

<p>Classification is only a function call away with:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(classifier text labels)

{'labels': ['breakfast', 'lunch', 'dinner'],
 'scores': [0.989736795425415, 0.007010194938629866, 0.003252972150221467]}
</code></pre>

<p>Breakfast is the winner. Notice that all the  probabilities add up to 1. This is because the default mode for <code>classify</code> uses <code>softmax</code>. We can change that so the categories are each considered independently with the <code>:multi-class</code> option.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(classifier text labels :multi_class true)
{'labels': ['breakfast', 'lunch', 'dinner'],
 'scores': [0.9959920048713684, 0.22608685493469238, 0.031050905585289]}
</code></pre>

<p>This is a really powerful technique for such an easy to use library. However, how can we do anything with it if we don&rsquo;t understand how it is working and get a handle on how to debug it. We need some level of trust in it for utility.</p>

<p>This is where LIME enters.</p>

<h3>Using LIME for Interpretable Models</h3>

<p>One of the biggest problems holding back applying state of the art machine learning models to real life problems is that of interpretability and trust. The <a href="https://github.com/marcotcr/lime">lime technique</a> is a well designed tool to help with this. One of the reasons that I really like it is that it is <em>model agnostic</em>. This means that you can use it with whatever code you want to use with it as long as you adhere to it&rsquo;s <em>api</em>. You need to provide it with the input and a function that will classify and return the probabilities in a numpy array.</p>

<p>The creation of the explainer is only a <code>require</code> away:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(require-python '[lime.lime_text :as lime])
(require-python 'numpy)


(def explainer (lime/LimeTextExplainer :class_names labels))
</code></pre>

<p>We need to create a function that will take in some text and then return the probabilities  for the labels. Since the zeroshot classifier will reorder the returning labels/probs by the value, we need to make sure that it will match up by index to the original labels.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defn predict-probs
  [text]
  (let [result (classifier text labels)
        result-scores (get result "scores")
        result-labels (get result "labels")
        result-map (zipmap result-labels result-scores)]
    (mapv (fn [cn]
            (get result-map cn))
          labels)))


(defn predict-texts
  [texts]
  (println "lime texts are " texts)
  (numpy/array (mapv predict-probs texts)))


 (predict-texts [text]) ;=&gt;  [[0.99718672 0.00281324]]
</code></pre>

<p>Finally we make an explanation for our text here. We are only using 6 features and 100 samples, to keep the cpus down, but in real life you would want to use closer to the default amount of <code>5000</code> samples. The samples are how the explainers work, it modifies the text over and over again and sees the difference in classification values. For example, one of the sample texts for our case is <code>' Toast with   bacon in the center with  syrup on .  with  sugar  desired.'</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def exp-result
  (py. explainer "explain_instance" text predict-texts
       :num_features 6
       :num_samples 100))


(py. exp-result "save_to_file" "explanation.html")
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51039510876_e547177bb2_h.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Now it becomes more clear. The model is using mainly the word <code>toast</code> to classify it as breakfast with supporting words also being <code>french</code>, <code>egg</code>, <code>maple</code>, and <code>syrup</code>. The word <code>the</code> is also in there too which could be an artifact of the low numbers of samples we used or not. But now at least we have the tools to dig in and understand.</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>Exciting advances are happening in Deep Learning and NLP. To make them truly useful,  we will need to continue to consider how to make them interpretable and debuggable.</p>

<p>As always, keep your Clojure REPL handy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on AI Debate 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2020/12/24/thoughts-on-ai-debate-2/"/>
    <updated>2020-12-24T10:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2020/12/24/thoughts-on-ai-debate-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://montrealartificialintelligence.com/aidebate2mosaic1440x720v8.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2>AI Debate 2 from Montreal.AI</h2>

<p>I had the pleasure of watching the second AI debate from Montreal.AI last night. The first AI debate occurred last year between <a href="https://yoshuabengio.org/">Yoshua Bengio</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Marcus">Gary Marcus</a> entitled <a href="https://montrealartificialintelligence.com/aidebate.html">“The Best Way Forward for AI”</a> in which Yoshua argued that Deep Learning could achieve General AI through its own paradigm, while Marcus argued that Deep Learning alone was not sufficient and needed a hybrid approach involving symbolics and inspiration from other disciplines.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>This interdisciplinary thread of Gary’s linked the two programs. The second AI debate was entitled <a href="https://montrealartificialintelligence.com/aidebate2.html">“Moving AI Forward: An Interdisciplinary Approach”</a> and reflected a broad panel that explored themes on architecture, neuroscience and psychology, and trust/ethics. The second program was not really a debate, but more of a showcase of ideas in the form of 3 minute presentations from the panelists and discussion around topics with Marcus serving as a capable moderator.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>The program aired Wednesday night and was 3 hours long. I watched it live with an unavoidable break in the middle to fetch dinner for my family, but the whole recording is up now on the <a href="https://montrealartificialintelligence.com/aidebate2.html">website</a>. Some of the highlights for me were thoughts around System 1 and System 2,  reinforcement learning, and the properties of evolution.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>There was much discussion around System 1 and System 2 in relation to AI. One of the author’s of the recently published paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2010.06002.pdf">“Thinking Fast and Slow in AI”</a>, <a href="https://researcher.watson.ibm.com/researcher/view.php?person=ibm-Francesca.Rossi2">Francesca Rossi</a> was a panelist as well as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Kahneman">Danny Kahneman</a> the author of “Thinking Fast and Slow”. Applying the abstraction of these sysems to AI with Deep Learning being System 1 is very appealing, however as Kahneman pointed out in his talk, this abstraction is leaky at its heart as the human System 1 encompasses much more than current AI system 1, (like a model of the world). It is interesting to think of one of the differences in human System 1 and System 2 in relation to one being fast and concurrent while the other is slower and sequential and laden with attention. Why is this so? Is this a constraint and design feature that we should bring to our AI design?</p>

<p><br></p>

<p><a href="http://www.incompleteideas.net/">Richard Sutton</a> gave a thought provoking talk on how reinforcement learning is the first fully implemented computational theory of intelligence. He pointed to <a href="https://apsc450computationalneuroscience.wordpress.com/marrs-three-levels-of-inquiry/">Marr’s three levels</a>  at which any information processing machine must be understood: hardware implementation, representation/algorithm, and finally the high level theory. That is: what is the goal of the computation? What logic can the strategy be carried out? AI has made great strides due to this computational theory. However, it is only one theory. We need more. I personally think that innovation and exploration in this area could lead to an exciting future in AI.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Evolution is a fundamental force that drives humans and the world around us. <a href="https://www.cs.ucf.edu/~kstanley/">Ken Stanely</a> reminded us that while computers dominate at solving problems, humans still rule at open-ended innovation over the millenia. The underlying properties of evolution still elude our deep understanding. Studying the core nature of this powerful phenomena is a very important area of research.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>The last question of the evening to all the panelists was the greatest Christmas gift of all - “Where do you want AI to go?”. The diversity of the answers reflected the broad hopes shared by many that will light the way to come. I’ll paraphrase some of the ones here:</p>

<ul>
<li>Want to understand fundamental laws and principles and use them to better the human condition.</li>
<li>Understand the different varieties of intelligence.</li>
<li>Want an intelligent and superfriendly apprentice. To understand self by emulating.</li>
<li>To move beyond GPT-3 remixing to really assisting creativity for humanity.</li>
<li>Hope that AI will amplify us and our abilities.</li>
<li>Use AI to help people understand what bias they have.</li>
<li>That humans will still have something to add after AI have mastered a domain</li>
<li>To understand the brain in the most simple and beautiful way.</li>
<li>Gain a better clarity and understanding of our own values by deciding which to endow our AI with.</li>
<li>Want the costs and benefits of AI to be distributed globally and economically.</li>
</ul>


<p><br></p>

<p>Thanks again Montreal.AI for putting together such a great program and sharing it with the community. I look forward to next year.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Merry Christmas everyone!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hugging Face GPT With Clojure]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2020/01/10/hugging-face-gpt-with-clojure/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-10T19:33:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2020/01/10/hugging-face-gpt-with-clojure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49364554561_6e4f4d0a51_w.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A new age in Clojure has dawned. We now have interop access to any python library with <a href="https://github.com/cnuernber/libpython-clj">libpython-clj</a>.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Let me pause a minute to repeat.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p><strong> You can now interop with ANY python library. </strong></p>

<p><br></p>

<p>I know. It&rsquo;s overwhelming. It took a bit for me to come to grips with it too.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take an example of something that I&rsquo;ve <em>always</em> wanted to do and have struggled with mightly finding a way to do it in Clojure:<br/>
I want to use the latest cutting edge GPT2 code out there to generate text.</p>

<p>Right now, that library is <a href="https://github.com/huggingface/transformers">Hugging Face Transformers</a>.<br/>
<br></p>

<p>Get ready. We will wrap that sweet hugging face code in Clojure parens!</p>

<h3>The setup</h3>

<p>The first thing you will need to do is to have python3 installed and the two libraries that we need:</p>

<p><br></p>

<ul>
<li>pytorch - <code>sudo pip3 install torch</code></li>
<li>hugging face transformers - <code>sudo pip3 install transformers</code></li>
</ul>


<p><br></p>

<p>Right now, some of you may not want to proceed. You might have had a bad relationship with Python in the past. It&rsquo;s ok, remember that some of us had bad relationships with Java, but still lead a happy and fulfilled life with Clojure and still can enjoy it from interop. The same is true with Python. Keep an open mind.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>There might be some others that don&rsquo;t want to have anything to do with Python and want to keep your Clojure pure. Well, that is a valid choice. But you are missing out on what the big, vibrant, and chaotic Python Deep Learning ecosystem has to offer.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>For those of you that are still along for the ride, let&rsquo;s dive in.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Your deps file should have just a single extra dependency in it:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">:deps {org.clojure/clojure {:mvn/version "1.10.1"}
        cnuernber/libpython-clj {:mvn/version "1.30"}}
</code></pre>

<h3>Diving Into Interop</h3>

<p>The first thing that we need to do is require the libpython library.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(ns gigasquid.gpt2
  (:require [libpython-clj.require :refer [require-python]]
            [libpython-clj.python :as py]))
</code></pre>

<p>It has a very nice <code>require-python</code> syntax that we will use to load the python libraries so that we can use them in our Clojure code.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(require-python '(transformers))
(require-python '(torch))
</code></pre>

<p>Here we are going to follow along with the OpenAI GPT-2 tutorial and translate it into interop code.
The original tutorial is <a href="https://huggingface.co/transformers/quickstart.html">here</a></p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take the python side first:</p>

<pre><code class="python">import torch
from transformers import GPT2Tokenizer, GPT2LMHeadModel

# Load pre-trained model tokenizer (vocabulary)
tokenizer = GPT2Tokenizer.from_pretrained('gpt2')
</code></pre>

<p>This is going to translate in our interop code to:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def tokenizer (py/$a transformers/GPT2Tokenizer from_pretrained "gpt2"))
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>py/$a</code> function is used to call attributes on a Python object. We get the <code>transformers/GPTTokenizer</code> object that we have available to use and call <code>from_pretrained</code> on it with the string argument <code>"gpt2"</code></p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Next in the Python tutorial is:</p>

<pre><code class="python"># Encode a text inputs
text = "Who was Jim Henson ? Jim Henson was a"
indexed_tokens = tokenizer.encode(text)

# Convert indexed tokens in a PyTorch tensor
tokens_tensor = torch.tensor([indexed_tokens])
</code></pre>

<p>This is going to translate to Clojure:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def text "Who was Jim Henson ? Jim Henson was a")
;; encode text input
(def indexed-tokens  (py/$a tokenizer encode text))
indexed-tokens ;=&gt;[8241, 373, 5395, 367, 19069, 5633, 5395, 367, 19069, 373, 257]

;; convert indexed tokens to pytorch tensor
(def tokens-tensor (torch/tensor [indexed-tokens]))
tokens-tensor
;; ([[ 8241,   373,  5395,   367, 19069,  5633,  5395,   367, 19069,   373,
;;    257]])
</code></pre>

<p>Here we are again using <code>py/$a</code> to call the <code>encode</code> method on the text. However, when we are just calling a function, we can do so directly with <code>(torch/tensor [indexed-tokens])</code>. We can even directly use vectors.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Again, you are doing this in the REPL, so you have full power for inspection and display of the python objects. It is a great interop experience - (cider even has doc information on the python functions in the minibuffer)!</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>The next part is to load the model itself. This will take a few minutes, since it has to download a big file from s3 and load it up.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>In Python:</p>

<pre><code class="python"># Load pre-trained model (weights)
model = GPT2LMHeadModel.from_pretrained('gpt2')
</code></pre>

<p>In Clojure:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">;;; Load pre-trained model (weights)
;;; Note: this will take a few minutes to download everything
(def model (py/$a transformers/GPT2LMHeadModel from_pretrained "gpt2"))
</code></pre>

<p>The next part is to run the model with the tokens and make the predictions.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Here the code starts to diverge a tiny bit.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Python:</p>

<pre><code class="python"># Set the model in evaluation mode to deactivate the DropOut modules
# This is IMPORTANT to have reproducible results during evaluation!
model.eval()

# If you have a GPU, put everything on cuda
tokens_tensor = tokens_tensor.to('cuda')
model.to('cuda')

# Predict all tokens
with torch.no_grad():
    outputs = model(tokens_tensor)
    predictions = outputs[0]

# get the predicted next sub-word (in our case, the word 'man')
predicted_index = torch.argmax(predictions[0, -1, :]).item()
predicted_text = tokenizer.decode(indexed_tokens + [predicted_index])
assert predicted_text == 'Who was Jim Henson? Jim Henson was a man'
</code></pre>

<p>And Clojure</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">;;; Set the model in evaluation mode to deactivate the DropOut modules
;;; This is IMPORTANT to have reproducible results during evaluation!
(py/$a model eval)


;;; Predict all tokens
(def predictions (py/with [r (torch/no_grad)]
                          (first (model tokens-tensor))))

;;; get the predicted next sub-word"
(def predicted-index (let [last-word-predictions (-&gt; predictions first last)
                           arg-max (torch/argmax last-word-predictions)]
                       (py/$a arg-max item)))

predicted-index ;=&gt;582

(py/$a tokenizer decode (-&gt; (into [] indexed-tokens)
                            (conj predicted-index)))

;=&gt; "Who was Jim Henson? Jim Henson was a man"
</code></pre>

<p>The main differences is that we are obviously not using the python array syntax in our code to manipulate the lists. For example, instead of using <code>outputs[0]</code>, we are going to use <code>(first outputs)</code>. But, other than that, it is a pretty good match, even with the <code>py/with</code>.</p>

<p>Also note that we are not making the call to configure it with GPU. This is intentionally left out to keep things simple for people to try it out. Sometimes, GPU configuration can be a bit tricky to set up depending on your system. For this example, you definitely won&rsquo;t need it since it runs fast enough on cpu. If you do want to do something more complicated later, like fine tuning, you will need to invest some time to get it set up.</p>

<h3>Doing Longer Sequences</h3>

<p>The next example in the tutorial goes on to cover generating longer text.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>Python</p>

<pre><code class="python">tokenizer = GPT2Tokenizer.from_pretrained("gpt2")
model = GPT2LMHeadModel.from_pretrained('gpt2')

generated = tokenizer.encode("The Manhattan bridge")
context = torch.tensor([generated])
past = None

for i in range(100):
    print(i)
    output, past = model(context, past=past)
    token = torch.argmax(output[0, :])

    generated += [token.tolist()]
    context = token.unsqueeze(0)

sequence = tokenizer.decode(generated)

print(sequence)
</code></pre>

<p>And Clojure</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def tokenizer (py/$a transformers/GPT2Tokenizer from_pretrained "gpt2"))
(def model (py/$a transformers/GPT2LMHeadModel from_pretrained "gpt2"))

(def generated (into [] (py/$a tokenizer encode "The Manhattan bridge")))
(def context (torch/tensor [generated]))


(defn generate-sequence-step [{:keys [generated-tokens context past]}]
  (let [[output past] (model context :past past)
        token (-&gt; (torch/argmax (first output)))
        new-generated  (conj generated-tokens (py/$a token tolist))]
    {:generated-tokens new-generated
     :context (py/$a token unsqueeze 0)
     :past past
     :token token}))

(defn decode-sequence [{:keys [generated-tokens]}]
  (py/$a tokenizer decode generated-tokens))

(loop [step {:generated-tokens generated
             :context context
             :past nil}
       i 10]
  (if (pos? i)
    (recur (generate-sequence-step step) (dec i))
    (decode-sequence step)))

;=&gt; "The Manhattan bridge\n\nThe Manhattan bridge is a major artery for"
</code></pre>

<p>The great thing is once we have it embedded in our code, there is no stopping. We can create a nice function:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defn generate-text [starting-text num-of-words-to-predict]
  (let [tokens (into [] (py/$a tokenizer encode starting-text))
        context (torch/tensor [tokens])
        result (reduce
                (fn [r i]
                  (println i)
                  (generate-sequence-step r))

                {:generated-tokens tokens
                 :context context
                 :past nil}

                (range num-of-words-to-predict))]
    (decode-sequence result)))
</code></pre>

<p>And finally we can generate some fun text!</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(generate-text "Clojure is a dynamic, general purpose programming language, combining the approachability and interactive" 20)

;=&gt; "Clojure is a dynamic, general purpose programming language, combining the approachability and interactive. It is a language that is easy to learn and use, and is easy to use for anyone"
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Clojure is a dynamic, general purpose programming language, combining the approachability and interactive. It is a language that is easy to learn and use, and is easy to use for anyone</strong></p>

<p><br></p>

<p>So true GPT2! So true!</p>

<h3>Wrap-up</h3>

<p>libpython-clj is a really powerful tool that will allow Clojurists to better explore, leverage, and integrate Python libraries into their code.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been really impressed with it so far and I encourage you to check it out.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>There is a <a href="https://github.com/gigasquid/libpython-clj-examples">repo with the examples</a> out there if you want to check them out. There is also an example of doing MXNet MNIST classification there as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating Deep Learning With clojure.spec]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2019/10/11/integrating-deep-learning-with-clojure-dot-spec/"/>
    <updated>2019-10-11T13:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2019/10/11/integrating-deep-learning-with-clojure-dot-spec</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>clojure.spec allows you to write specifications for data and use them for validation. It also provides a generative aspect that allows for robust testing as well as an additional way to understand your data through manual inspection. The dual nature of validation and generation is a natural fit for deep learning models that consist of paired discriminator/generator models.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p><strong><strong>TLDR: In this post we show that you can leverage the dual nature of clojure.spec&rsquo;s validator/generator to incorporate a deep learning model&rsquo;s classifier/generator.</strong></strong></p>

<p><br></p>

<p>A common use of clojure.spec is at the boundaries to validate that incoming data is indeed in the expected form. Again, this is boundary is a fitting place to integrate models for the deep learning paradigm and our traditional software code.</p>

<p>Before we get into the deep learning side of things, let&rsquo;s take a quick refresher on how to use clojure.spec.</p>

<h2>quick view of clojure.spec</h2>

<p>To create a simple spec for keywords that are cat sounds, we can use <code>s/def</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(s/def ::cat-sounds #{:meow :purr :hiss})
</code></pre>

<p>To do the validation, you can use the <code>s/valid?</code> function.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(s/valid? ::cat-sounds :meow) ;=&gt; true
(s/valid? ::cat-sounds :bark) ;=&gt; false
</code></pre>

<p>For the generation side of things, we can turn the spec into generator and sample it.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(gen/sample (s/gen ::cat-sounds))
;=&gt;(:hiss :hiss :hiss :meow :meow :purr :hiss :meow :meow :meow)
</code></pre>

<p>There is the ability to compose specs by adding them together with <code>s/and</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(s/def ::even-number (s/and int? even?))
(gen/sample (s/gen ::even-number))
;=&gt; (0 0 -2 2 0 10 -4 8 6 8)
</code></pre>

<p>We can also control the generation by creating a custom generator using <code>s/with-gen</code>.
In the following the spec is only that the data be a general string, but using the custom generator, we can restrict the output to only be a certain set of example cat names.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(s/def ::cat-name
  (s/with-gen
    string?
    #(s/gen #{"Suki" "Bill" "Patches" "Sunshine"})))

(s/valid? ::cat-name "Peaches") ;=&gt; true
(gen/sample (s/gen ::cat-name))
;; ("Patches" "Sunshine" "Sunshine" "Suki" "Suki" "Sunshine"
;;  "Suki" "Patches" "Sunshine" "Suki")
</code></pre>

<p>For further information on clojure.spec, I whole-heartedly recommend the <a href="https://clojure.org/guides/spec">spec Guide</a>. But, now with a basic overview of spec, we can move on to creating specs for our Deep Learning models.</p>

<h2>Creating specs for Deep Learning Models</h2>

<p>In previous posts, we covered making <a href="https://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2019/08/16/simple-autoencoder/">simple autoencoders for handwritten digits</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48647524478_ca35bef78f_n.jpg" alt="handwritten digits" /></p>

<p>Then, we made models that would:</p>

<ul>
<li>Take an image of a digit and give you back the string value (ex: &ldquo;2&rdquo;) - <a href="https://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2019/08/30/focus-on-the-discriminator/">post</a></li>
<li>Take a string number value and give you back a digit image. - <a href="https://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2019/09/06/focus-on-the-generator/">post</a></li>
</ul>


<p>We will use both of the models to make a spec with a custom generator.</p>

<p><br></p>

<p><em>Note: For the sake of simplicity, some of the supporting code is left out. But if you want to see the whole code, it is on <a href="(https://github.com/gigasquid/clojure-mxnet-autoencoder/blob/master/src/clojure_mxnet_autoencoder/model_specs.clj">github</a>)</em></p>

<p><br></p>

<p>With the help of the trained discriminator model, we can make a function that takes in an image and returns the number string value.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defn discriminate [image]
  (-&gt; (m/forward discriminator-model {:data [image]})
      (m/outputs)
      (ffirst)
      (ndarray/argmax-channel)
      (ndarray/-&gt;vec)
      (first)
      (int)))
</code></pre>

<p>Let&rsquo;s test it out with a test-image:</p>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48881532151_251e30840e_s.jpg" alt="test-discriminator-image" /></p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(discriminate my-test-image) ;=&gt; 6
</code></pre>

<p>Likewise, with the trained generator model, we can make a function that takes a string number and returns the corresponding image.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defn generate [label]
  (-&gt; (m/forward generator-model {:data [(ndarray/array [label] [batch-size])]})
      (m/outputs)
      (ffirst)))
</code></pre>

<p>Giving it a test drive as well:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def generated-test-image (generate 3))
(viz/im-sav {:title "generated-image"
             :output-path "results/"
             :x (ndarray/reshape generated-test-image [batch-size 1 28 28])})
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48881532451_023de68ddb_s.jpg" alt="generated-test-image" /></p>

<p>Great! Let&rsquo;s go ahead and start writing specs. First let&rsquo;s make a quick spec to describe a MNIST number - which is a single digit between 0 and 9.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(s/def ::mnist-number (s/and int? #(&lt;= 0 % 9)))
(s/valid? ::mnist-number 3) ;=&gt; true
(s/valid? ::mnist-number 11) ;=&gt; false
(gen/sample (s/gen ::mnist-number))
;=&gt; (0 1 0 3 5 3 7 5 0 1)
</code></pre>

<p>We now have both parts to validate and generate and can create a spec for it.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(s/def ::mnist-image
    (s/with-gen
      #(s/valid? ::mnist-number (discriminate %))
      #(gen/fmap (fn [n]
                   (do (ndarray/copy (generate n))))
                 (s/gen ::mnist-number))))
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>::mnist-number</code> spec is used for the validation after the <code>discriminate</code> model is used. On the generator side, we use the generator for the <code>::mnist-number</code> spec and feed that into the deep learning generator model to get sample images.</p>

<p>We have a test function that will help us test out this new spec, called <code>test-model-spec</code>. It will return a map with the following form:</p>

<pre><code>{:spec name-of-the-spec
 :valid? whether or not the `s/valid?` called on the test value is true or not
 :sample-values This calls the discriminator model on the generated values
 }
</code></pre>

<p>It will also write an image of all the sample images to a file named <code>sample-spec-name</code></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s try it on our test image:</p>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48881532151_251e30840e_s.jpg" alt="test-discriminator-image" /></p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(s/valid? ::mnist-image my-test-image) ;=&gt; true


(test-model-spec ::mnist-image my-test-image)
;; {:spec "mnist-image"
;;  :valid? true
;;  :sample-values [0 0 0 1 3 1 0 2 7 3]}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48882235262_1e0dd7b758_q.jpg" alt="sample-mnist-image" /></p>

<p>Pretty cool!</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s do some more specs. But first, our spec is going to be a bit repetitive, so we&rsquo;ll make a quick macro to make things easier.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defmacro def-model-spec [spec-key spec discriminate-fn generate-fn]
    `(s/def ~spec-key
       (s/with-gen
         #(s/valid? ~spec (~discriminate-fn %))
         #(gen/fmap (fn [n#]
                      (do (ndarray/copy (~generate-fn n#))))
                    (s/gen ~spec)))))
</code></pre>

<h3>More Specs - More Fun</h3>

<p>This time let&rsquo;s define an even mnist image spec</p>

<pre><code class="clojure"> (def-model-spec ::even-mnist-image
    (s/and ::mnist-number even?)
    discriminate
    generate)

  (test-model-spec ::even-mnist-image my-test-image)

  ;; {:spec "even-mnist-image"
  ;;  :valid? true
  ;;  :sample-values [0 0 2 0 8 2 2 2 0 0]}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48882253157_02e45d3132_q.jpg" alt="sample-even-mnist-image" /></p>

<p>And Odds</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">  (def-model-spec ::odd-mnist-image
    (s/and ::mnist-number odd?)
    discriminate
    generate)

  (test-model-spec ::odd-mnist-image my-test-image)

  ;; {:spec "odd-mnist-image"
  ;;  :valid? false
  ;;  :sample-values [5 1 5 1 3 3 3 1 1 1]}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48881548138_c18850f806_q.jpg" alt="sample-odd-mnist-image" /></p>

<p>Finally, let&rsquo;s do Odds that are over 2!</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">  (def-model-spec ::odd-over-2-mnist-image
    (s/and ::mnist-number odd? #(&gt; % 2))
    discriminate
    generate)

  (test-model-spec ::odd-over-2-mnist-image my-test-image)

  ;; {:spec "odd-over-2-mnist-image"
  ;;  :valid? false
  ;;  :sample-values [3 3 3 5 3 5 7 7 7 3]}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48882089776_6f55416418_q.jpg" alt="sample-odd-over-2-mnist-image" /></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>We have shown some of the potential of integrating deep learning models with Clojure. clojure.spec is a powerful tool and it can be leveraged in new and interesting ways for both deep learning and AI more generally.</p>

<p>I hope that more people are intrigued to experiment and take a further look into what we can do in this area.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Focus on the Generator]]></title>
    <link href="http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2019/09/06/focus-on-the-generator/"/>
    <updated>2019-09-06T18:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://gigasquid.github.io/blog/2019/09/06/focus-on-the-generator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/smigla-bobinski/19705409981/in/album-72157647756733695/" title="SIMULACRA by Karina Smigla-Bobinski"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/330/19705409981_4e0ae93572.jpg" width="500" height="267" alt="SIMULACRA by Karina Smigla-Bobinski"></a><script async src="http://gigasquid.github.io//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In this first post of this series, we took a look at a <a href="https://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2019/08/16/simple-autoencoder/">simple autoencoder</a>. It took and image and transformed it back to an image. Then, we <a href="https://gigasquidsoftware.com/blog/2019/08/30/focus-on-the-discriminator/">focused in on the disciminator</a> portion of the model, where we took an image and transformed it to a label. Now, we focus in on the generator portion of the model do the inverse operation: we transform a label to an image. In recap:</p>

<ul>
<li>Autoencoder: image -> image</li>
<li>Discriminator: image -> label</li>
<li>Generator: label -> image (This is what we are doing now!)</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48689260086_11fe4b089b_b.jpg" alt="generator" /></p>

<h2>Still Need Data of Course</h2>

<p>Nothing changes here. We are still using the MNIST handwritten digit set and have an input and out to our model.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def
  train-data
  (mx-io/mnist-iter {:image (str data-dir "train-images-idx3-ubyte")
                     :label (str data-dir "train-labels-idx1-ubyte")
                     :input-shape [784]
                     :flat true
                     :batch-size batch-size
                     :shuffle true}))

(def
  test-data (mx-io/mnist-iter
             {:image (str data-dir "t10k-images-idx3-ubyte")
              :label (str data-dir "t10k-labels-idx1-ubyte")
              :input-shape [784]
              :batch-size batch-size
              :flat true
              :shuffle true}))

(def input (sym/variable "input"))
(def output (sym/variable "input_"))
</code></pre>

<h2>The Generator Model</h2>

<p>The model does change to one hot encode the label for the number. Other than that, it&rsquo;s pretty much the exact same second half of the autoencoder model.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defn get-symbol []
  (as-&gt; input data
    (sym/one-hot "onehot" {:indices data :depth 10})
    ;; decode
    (sym/fully-connected "decode1" {:data data :num-hidden 50})
    (sym/activation "sigmoid3" {:data data :act-type "sigmoid"})

    ;; decode
    (sym/fully-connected "decode2" {:data data :num-hidden 100})
    (sym/activation "sigmoid4" {:data data :act-type "sigmoid"})

    ;;output
    (sym/fully-connected "result" {:data data :num-hidden 784})
    (sym/activation "sigmoid5" {:data data :act-type "sigmoid"})

    (sym/linear-regression-output {:data data :label output})))

(def data-desc
  (first
   (mx-io/provide-data-desc train-data)))
(def label-desc
  (first
   (mx-io/provide-label-desc train-data)))
</code></pre>

<p>When binding the shapes to the model, we now need to specify that the input data shapes is the label instead of the image and the output of the model is going to be the image.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def
  model
  ;;; change data shapes to label shapes
  (-&gt; (m/module (get-symbol) {:data-names ["input"] :label-names ["input_"]})
      (m/bind {:data-shapes [(assoc label-desc :name "input")]
               :label-shapes [(assoc data-desc :name "input_")]})
      (m/init-params {:initializer  (initializer/uniform 1)})
      (m/init-optimizer {:optimizer (optimizer/adam {:learning-rage 0.001})})))

(def my-metric (eval-metric/mse))
</code></pre>

<h2>Training</h2>

<p>The training of the model is pretty straight forward. Just being mindful that we are using hte batch-label, (number label),  as the input and and validating with the batch-data, (image).</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defn train [num-epochs]
  (doseq [epoch-num (range 0 num-epochs)]
    (println "starting epoch " epoch-num)
    (mx-io/do-batches
     train-data
     (fn [batch]
       ;;; change input to be the label
       (-&gt; model
           (m/forward {:data (mx-io/batch-label batch)
                       :label (mx-io/batch-data batch)})
           (m/update-metric my-metric (mx-io/batch-data batch))
           (m/backward)
           (m/update))))
    (println "result for epoch " epoch-num " is "
             (eval-metric/get-and-reset my-metric))))
</code></pre>

<h2>Results Before Training</h2>

<pre><code class="clojure">(def my-test-batch (mx-io/next test-data))
  ;;; change to input labels
  (def test-labels (mx-io/batch-label my-test-batch))
  (def preds (m/predict-batch model {:data test-labels} ))
  (viz/im-sav {:title "before-training-preds"
               :output-path "results/"
               :x (ndarray/reshape (first preds) [100 1 28 28])})

  (-&gt;&gt; test-labels first ndarray/-&gt;vec (take 10))
  ;=&gt; (6.0 1.0 0.0 0.0 3.0 1.0 4.0 8.0 0.0 9.0)
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48689304281_a41bf39353.jpg" alt="before training" /></p>

<p>Not very impressive&hellip; Let&rsquo;s train</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(train 3)

starting epoch  0
result for epoch  0  is  
[mse 0.0723091]
starting epoch  1
result for epoch  1  is  [mse 0.053891845]
starting epoch  2
result for epoch  2  is  [mse 0.05337505]
</code></pre>

<h2>Results After Training</h2>

<pre><code class="clojure"> (def my-test-batch (mx-io/next test-data))
  (def test-labels (mx-io/batch-label my-test-batch))
  (def preds (m/predict-batch model {:data test-labels}))
  (viz/im-sav {:title "after-training-preds"
               :output-path "results/"
               :x (ndarray/reshape (first preds) [100 1 28 28])})
  (-&gt;&gt; test-labels first ndarray/-&gt;vec (take 10))

  ;=&gt;   (9.0 5.0 7.0 1.0 8.0 6.0 6.0 0.0 8.0 1.0)
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48689328481_338416ba7c.jpg" alt="after training" /></p>

<p>Cool! The first row is indeed</p>

<p><code>(9.0 5.0 7.0 1.0 8.0 6.0 6.0 0.0 8.0 1.0)</code></p>

<h2>Save Your Model</h2>

<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to save the generator model off - we are going to use it next time.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(m/save-checkpoint model {:prefix "model/generator" :epoch 2})
</code></pre>

<p>Happy Deep Learning until next time &hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
